Register of the Alex N. Kniazeff (Aleksei Nikolaevich Kniazev) Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alex N. Kniazeff (Aleksei Nikolaevich Kniazev) papers
1911-1993
2000C46
Hoover Institution Archives
43 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 17 microfilm reels (13.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, minutes, financial records, bulletins, personal documents, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the Russian Boy Scouts movement abroad and to Russian émigré affairs. In part, microfilm.
Kniazeff, Alex N., 1909-1993
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
In part, originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Born at Tsitsikhar station on the Chinese Eastern Railway on 5 August 1909, where his father, an army engineer officer, was stationed, Kniazev spent the first half of his life in China. As his father was transferred to Manchuria station, where he was commandant during the Russian Civil War, and later to Harbin, where he was assistant commandant, A. N. Kniazeff moved with him, graduating from American Methodist College in Harbin in 1927. From 1927 to 1933 he was a student at Harbin Polytechnic Institute, receiving his baccalaureate degree in electrical and mechanical engineering. Simultaneously, he completed a training course at the Russkii Obshchevoinskii soiuz military academy in 1934.
Following his graduation, he moved to Tientsin, where he worked as an engineer for a number of companies until 1945, when he was forced to escape to Shanghai. He was interned at Tubabao refugee camp until January 1951, when he finally arrived in San Francisco. From 1952 to 1955 he was an instructor at the Army Language School in Monterey until he was able to secure employment closer to his field of specialization, first as an instrumentation designer for Bechtel Corporation (1955-1958), and then at Pacific Gas and Electric Company until retirement (1958-1974).
As a member of the Russian boy scouts since 1922 in Harbin, he rose to become Chief Russian Scout of St. George's Knights (Natsional'naia organizatsiia russkikh skautov). Kniazeff died in San Francisco in 1993.
Chronology
1909 August 5 (N.S.) Born, Tsitsihar, China
1933 Degree, Electrical and Mechanical Engineering, Harbin Polytechnic Institute, Harbin, China
1935-1948 Engineering and administrative positions, Kailan Mining Administration, Tientsin, China Scoutmaster, Tientsin, China
1941 April 27 Married Eugenia Smikovska
1949-1951 General Consulting Engineer, International Refugee Organization, Tubabao, Samar, Philippines
1952-1955 Instructor of Russian, U. S. Army Language School, Monterey, California
1955-1958 Instrumentation Designer, Bechtel Corporation, San Francisco, California
1958-1974 Senior Draftsman, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, San Francisco, California
1959- Scoutmaster, Natsional'naia organizatsiia rossiiskikh skautov (St. George's Knights)
1993 Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of correspondence, clippings and other matter reflecting Kniazeff's involvement in various émigré organizations. He was a member of the San Francisco Trans-Baikal Cossacks' Stanitza and of the Harbin Polytechnic Alumni Association, and senior scoutmaster of the Natsional'naia Organizatsiia Russkikh Skautov (National Organization of Russian Scouts, or St. George's Knights, as it was incorporated in California). Most of the collection relates to the history of the Russian Boy Scout movement abroad, particularly for the period 1963-1975.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Natsional'naia organizatsiia russkikh skautov.; Boy Scouts.; Russia.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1918-1977 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes family documents and illustrated manuscript by Kniazeff's father on carpentry, as well as personal, employment and army reserve files on Kniazeff's career, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Correspondence, 1969-1987 (Box 1)
  Arranged chronologically by correspondent
- Natsional'naia Organizatsiia Russkikh Skautov (St. George's Knights, Inc.), 1918-1989 (Box 2-12)
  Consists of correspondence, orders, minutes, publications and other materials, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Subject File, 1926-1989 (Box 12-16)
  Consists mainly of materials relating to the organizations Kniazeff was involved in, arranged alphabetically by name of organization, and therein by physical form
- Printed Matter, 1917-1987 (Box 17-18)
  Includes calendars, clippings, leaflets, programs and issues of periodicals, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Material has not yet been described. (Box 19-45)
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1918-1977 (Box 1)
  - General - "Personal file,"., 1930-1977 (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes awards, certificates, commendations, diploma and other documents relating to Kniazeff's education, employment and social activities
  - Family
    - Kniazev, Nikolai Ivanovich
      - Identity papers, 1918-1949 (Folder 1: 2)
      - Writing entitled "Plotnichnoe iskusstvo,", n.d. (Folder 1: 3)
        Holograph
    - Kniazeva, Nadezhda Alekseevna. (Folder 1: 4)
      Identity document, 1938
  - Grievance against Pacific Gas and Electric, 1969-1972 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Military service in the U. S. Army Active Reserve, 1954-1967 (Folder 1: 6)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1969-1987
  - General, 1972-1987 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Balakshin, P., 1975 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Koslovsky, B. and N., 1973 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Kosterin, A. and V., 1973 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Magerovsky, L. F., 1984 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Mamchenko, Onisim, 1975 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Mescher, M., 1981 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Tokmakov, Mstislav Vladimirovich, 1970 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Turkin, A., 1969 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Verstak, V., 1973 (Folder 1: 16)
- NATSIONAL'NAIA ORGANIZATSIIA RUSSKIKH SKAUTOV (St. George's Knights, Inc.), 1918-1989 (Box 2)
  - General
    - Central staff, 1966-1972 (Folder 2: 1)
    - 1 st Burlingame Druzhina, 1965-1975 (Folder 2: 2)
    - 1 st San Francisco Druzhina, 1966-1972
      - General (Folder 2: 3)
      - Orders, minutes and circulars (Folder 2: 4)
    - Summer camps. (Folder 2: 5)
      Guides, handbooks and documents relating to their organization, 1965-1970
  - Correspondence.
    Includes clippings, personal correspondence and other forms of material
    - General
      - Circulars, 1960-1969 (Folder 2: 6)
      - Incoming and outgoing letters
        - 1949-1962 (Folder 2: 7)
        - 1963 (Box-folder 3: 1)
        - 1964 (Folder 3: 2)
        - 1965 (Folder 3: 3)
        - 1966 January-June (Folder 3: 4)
        - 1966 July-December (Box-folder 4: 1)
        - 1967
          - January-May (Folder 4: 2)
          - June-September (Folder 4: 3)
          - October-December (Folder 4: 4)
        - 1968
          - January-February (Folder 5: 1)
          - March-May (Folder 5: 2)
          - June-July (Folder 5: 3)
          - August-October (Folder 5: 4)
          - November-December (Folder 5: 5)
        - 1969
          - January-March (Folder 5: 6)
          - April-May (Box-folder 6: 1)
          - June-July (Folder 6: 2)
          - August-December (Folder 6: 3)
        - 1970
          - January-March (Folder 6: 4)
          - April-June (Box-folder 7: 1)
          - July-December (Folder 7: 2)
        - 1971
          - January-April (Folder 7: 3)
          - May-July (Folder 7: 4)
          - August-December (Box-folder 8: 1)
        - 1972
          - January-July (Folder 8: 2)
          - August-December (Folder 8: 3)
        - 1973 (Folder 8: 4)
        - 1974 (Box 9)
          - January-March (Folder 9: 1)
          - April-May (Folder 9: 2)
          - June-December (Folder 9: 3)
        - 1975-1977 (Folder 9: 4)
        - 1978-1989 (Folder 9: 5)
    - Mercier (Mers'e), V. V., 1972-1979 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Odinets, M. D., 1972-1979 (Folder 10: 2)
    - Sedliarevich, N. M., 1973-1979 (Folder 10: 3)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1959-1974 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Orders
    - Senior Russian Scout (O. I. Pantiukhov), 1964-1970 (Folder 10: 5)
    - North American Section of N.O.R.S., 1960-1973 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Publications.
    Listed alphabetically by title
    - Davaite spoem: Sbornik skautskikh pesen, 1965 (Folder 10: 7)
      Typescript
    - Informatsionnyi biulleten'.
      - #1 (1974) - 8 (1975) (Folder 10: 8)
      - #9 (1975) - 15 (1979) (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Listok ispytanii na razriady, c. 1938 (Folder 11: 2)
      Printed copy
    - Programma na 3-ii i 2-oi razriady, n.d. (Folder 11: 3)
    - Russkie skauty, 1909-1969
      - Typescript. (Folder 11: 4)
        Consists of materials collected by Kniazeff. May include material not present in published edition
      - Printed copy (Folder 11: 5)
    - Skautenok, #4 (1963) - 9 (1965) (Folder 11: 6)
    - Vpered, #4 (1959), 8-11 (1960) (Folder 11: 7)
  - Writings of scoutmaster E. Orlova. (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Miscellany (Folder 12: 2)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1926-1989
  - American-Russian San Francisco Bay Region Credit Union.
    Clippings, correspondence, financial statements, reports, printed matter and other materials relating to this organization's activities
    - 1961-1966 (Folder 12: 3)
    - 1967 (Folder 12: 4)
    - 1968 (Folder 12: 5)
    - 1969 (Folder 12: 6)
    - 1970 (Box 13)
      - January-May (Folder 13: 1)
      - June-December (Folder 13: 2)
    - 1971-1975 (Folder 13: 3)
  - CORO Corporation (Consolidated Real Estate Opportunities Corporation).
    Consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence, financial statements, annual and semi-annual reports and other materials
    - 1964-1969 (Folder 13: 4)
    - 1970-1973 (Folder 13: 5)
  - Kharbinskii Politekhnicheskii Institut (Harbin Polytechnic Institute). Primarily composed of documents relating to the activities of its alumni association.
    Includes clippings of reminiscences and other related matter
    - 1950-1967 (Folder 13: 6)
    - 1968-1971 (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - 1972-1989 (Folder 14: 2)
  - Obshche-kazachii soiuz v g. San Frantsisko (All Cossack's Union of San Francisco).
    Includes material pertaining to other Cossack organizations
    - General
      - 1926-1970 (Folder 14: 3)
      - 1971-1973 (Folder 14: 4)
      - 1974-1982 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Printed matter. (Folder 15: 2)
      Includes Kazachii klich, #1 (March 1954) and Kazak, #176-192 (1963-1964, incomplete)
  - Organizatsiia rossiiskikh iunykh razvedchikov (Folder 15: 3)
  - Rossiiskii natsional'no-trudovoi soiuz (Folder 15: 4)
  - Russian Center, San Francisco (Russkii Tsentr) (Folder 15: 5)
  - Russian Community Club, Inc., San Mateo, California (Russkii Obshchestvennyi Klub) (Folder 15: 6)
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' (Orthodox Eastern Church, Russian). (Box-folder 16: 1)
    Includes award presented by Archbishop Viktor of China to G. M. Ivanov, 1940 October 12
  - Society of Russian Veterans, San Francisco (Obshchestvo russkikh veteranov Velikoi voiny). (Folder 16: 2)
    Includes typed draft of B. B. Filimonov's "Bor'ba v Zaural'e," 1935, published serially in the Society's journal, Viestnik Obshchestva veteranov Velikoi voiny, correspondence relating to its publication and author, and other materials for publication in the journal, as well as documents relating to the organization's other activities
  - Trans-Baikal Cossacks' Stanitza of San Francisco (Folder 16: 3)
  - Miscellany (Folder 16: 4)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1917-1987 (Box 17)
  - Books (Folder 17: 1)
  - Calendars (Folder 17: 2)
  - Clippings (Folder 17: 3-4)
  - Leaflets (Folder 17: 5)
  - Periodicals. (Folder 17: 6-7)
    Includes issues of Nash vestnik (Tubabao), 1951 and Kharbinskoe vremia, #17 (1941)
  - Periodicals. (Box-folder 18: 1-3)
    Includes holiday issues of Russkaia zhizn', 1964-1969
  - Programs. (Folder 18: 4-5)
    Mostly from San Francisco in the 1950s-1960s, but some from Russia, 1917 and possibly earlier - musical evenings, balls and school productions